Guide to the Gerald R. Brong Papers 1967-1980
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Gerald R. Brong Papers
1967-1980
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 822
Brong, Gerald R.
1 linear foot of shelf space 1 box
Available here are the professional papers, predominantly from the 1970s, of Washington State University library media specialist and educational technologist Gerald R. Brong. The collection comprises correspondence, papers for publication and presentation, materials from meetings including the 1979 White House Conference on Library and Information Services, and documents related to the work of statewide and national task forces, of professional associations, and of Library Faculty at Washington State University.
Gerald "Jerry" Brong began his Washington State University Libraries career as an audiovisual specialist and then widened his pursuits in the 1970s to educational technology and technology's application in library systems. Brong received his Bachelor's and then Master of Education degree from Central Washington University and worked for a few years as a teacher in the Tacoma Public Schools before beginning his employment in 1964 as the Assistant Director in the Audio-Visual Center of Washington State University Libraries and within a year as Library Faculty. He completed his Doctorate in Education (Ed.D) at Washington State University in 1972. From 1974 to 1975 he served with the Washington State Library in Olympia as Director of the Library Futures Planning Task Force for the state while continuing to hold his WSU position. By 1977 the Audio-Visual Center had become Instructional Media Services with Brong as Assistant Director and Director of Faculty Services. He resigned from that position in 1982 and left WSU.
This collection consists of professional papers of Gerald "Jerry" Brong while he worked at Washington State University Libraries during the 1970s. The materials reflect Brong's activities during the first years of the Information Age when libraries diversified not only access to materials through early online networks and databases but also the types of materials they housed especially non-print ones. Brong devoted his attention to the WSU Libraries' growing collection of audiovisual resources, to their use in education, and increasingly to educational technology. His expertise in non-print media and interest in technology's application to library services led to involvement in statewide and national efforts. Among those were his leadership of the Washington State Library Futures Planning Task Force from 1974 to 1975 to develop intrastate cooperation mechanisms to meet the needs of library users in the present and future, advocacy for recognition of the audiovisual specialty nationally through the Association for Educational Communication and Technology and within Washington State's librarian certification, contributions to various divisions of the American Library Association, and participation in the 1979 White House Conference on Library and Information Services.
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series 1: Working Papers, Presentations, Publications, and Related Correspondence, 1969-1980.
This series groups drafts of papers for publication and speeches for conferences with working papers for various task forces at state and national levels and includes related correspondence. Arrangement in large part preserves Brong's original foldering and proceeds chronologically.
Series 2: Professional Associations, Political Advocacy, and Related Correspondence, 1967-1980.
Correspondence and materials related to activities of professional organizations such as the American Library Association and Association for Educational Communication and Technology and to political advocacy regarding federal legislation affecting libraries and higher education are arranged by organization or conference and then chronologically.
Series 3: Washington State University Committees, 1970-1979
This series gathers memoranda and materials distributed to and by WSU Library Faculty.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Gerald Brong donated this collection to the Washington State University Libraries in 1980 (MS 1980-53).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University -- Faculty -- Archives
Audio-visual education; Audio-visual library service; Instructional materials centers
Colleges and Universities.
- Series 1: Working Papers, Presentations, Publications, and Related Correspondence, 1969-1980
  Series scope and content: This series groups drafts of papers for publication and speeches for conferences with working papers for various task forces at state and national levels and includes related correspondence. Arrangement in large part preserves Brong's original foldering and proceeds chronologically.
  - Correspondence and article manuscript "Creating a New Procedure" that appeared in 1970 November 15 Library Journal., 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and article manuscripts for Bowker Annual of Library and Book Trade Information: "Non-Print Media--1971, the Year of Minimal Change," published 1972 Bowker Annual; "What LSCA Has Done for Us in Washington State," unpublished., 1971-1972 (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence regarding article "Educational Communications" for Advances in Librarianship, Volume V, 1975.., 1973-1974 (Folder 3)
  - Materials related to attendance at 1975 September 9 "Tuesday at the White House" meeting with 32 library community representatives from across United States., 1974-1975 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and article drafts for "The State of Washington's Search for Intrastate Cooperation," Library Trends, October 1975., 1975 (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence concerning Pierian Press serials Multi-Media Reviews Index later Media Review Digest and Reference Services Review with copy of November/December 1972 issue., 1971-1975 (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and manuscripts of two book reviews prepared for Journal of Library Automation., 1975 (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and article manuscript for "Educational Media and the Network" that appeared in Educational Media Yearbook 1975-1976., 1974-1976 (Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Rod Swartz, State Librarian of Washington, including working paper entitled "A Strategy for Maximum Involvement in Goal Attainment in the Library Services System of Washington State.", 1976 March (Folder 9)
  - Materials connected to presentation at 1976 Western Society for Physical Education of College Women conference., 1976-1977 (Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Library Trends journal staff regarding proposal for issue on educational technology futures., 1976-1977 (Folder 11)
  - Notes from comments on a paper delivered during 1977 Allerton Conference on Communication, Control, and Computing at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign., 1977 (Folder 12)
  - 1976 working paper: "Project Media Base: A National Data Base for Audiovisual Resources" with 1978 presentation notes and update with conclusions and recommendations., 1976, 1978 (Folder 13)
  - Correspondence regarding chairing of panel discussion at 1978 Association for Educational Communication and Technology (AECT) convention in the Division of Educational Media Management program., 1977-1978 (Folder 14)
  - Short courses about cataloging audio-visual materials sponsored by the School of Librarianship, University of Washington, 1977 August 15-16 in Spokane, and 1978 June 12-13 in Seattle: program, workshop evaluation, and related correspondence., 1977-1978 (Folder 15)
  - Correspondence regarding Fair Use and Free Inquiry: Copyright Law and the New Media, ed. John Shelton and Bernard Timberg, Ablex Publishing Co., Norwood, NJ., 1978 (Folder 16)
  - The Information Cycle: From an Educational Technologist's Viewpoint speech: outline dated 1978 January 16., 1978 (Folder 17)
  - Technology and the Technician: Educational Technology and Instructional Media Programs in Higher Education speech delivered as part of the Classified Library Employees of Washington State program during the Washington Library Association annual conference, 1978 April 21: speech outline and related correspondence., 1978 (Folder 18)
  - Materials associated with Library Information Technology Association (LITA) of American Library Association (ALA) "Management of Information for the 80's" Institute, 1978 September 27-29., 1978 (Folder 19)
  - Speech about Educational Technology evidently given at the Spring Faculty/Staff Luncheon of the Washington State University Department of Physical Education for Men, 1978 May 31: correspondence, speech outline, and luncheon invitation; Pullman Kiwanis Club Certificate of Appreciation for presentation given, 1979 April 26., 1978-1979 (Folder 20)
  - Communication Takes More Than Technology presentation and related materials for Northwest District of American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation, and Dance., 1978-1979 (Folder 21)
  - Position/Working Papers for AECT with notes: 1972 "Divisions--The Programming Role"; 1977 "Library Information Service: The Target is Learning" in preparation for 1979 White House Conference on Library and Information Services (WHCLIS)., 1972, 1977-1979 (Folder 22)
  - Panelist on Seattle KSTW-TV "Access - Community Forums" program about the future of libraries associated with Washington State Governor's Conference on Library and Information Systems: correspondence and program report., Mar-79 (Folder 23)
  - Expanding Educational Options in the 80's: Cable TV and the Educator, Conference at University of Texas at Arlington: conference materials and presentation given for "Libraries and Cable" session., 1980 March 6 (Folder 24)
- Series 2: Professional Associations, Political Advocacy, and Related Correspondence, 1967-1980
  Series scope and content: Correspondence and materials related to activities of professional organizations such as the American Library Association and Association for Educational Communication and Technology and to political advocacy regarding federal legislation affecting libraries and higher education are arranged by organization or conference and then chronologically.
  - American Library Association (ALA) correspondence regarding ALA Information Science and Automation Division - Audiovisual Section and ALA Library Information Technology Association Division (LITA)., 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - ALA LITA Education Committee and LITA Governors' Advisory Committee., 1978-1979 (Folder 26)
  - ALA Information Packet for the White House Conference on Library and Information Services (WHCLIS)., 1979 (Folder 27)
  - ALA concerning WHCLIS: correspondence, newsletters, programs, and notes., 1975-1980 (Folder 28)
  - WHCLIS: correspondence and materials related to state delegates to 1979 WHCLIS and Association for Educational Communications and Technology (AECT) involvement., 1977-1980 (Folder 29)
  - AECT Long-Range Planning Committee: correspondence and reports, 1971-1972 (Folder 30)
  - AECT Convention: correspondence including that regarding National Commission on Libraries and Information Science., 1973, 1976 (Folder 31)
  - AECT 1975: Task Force Report "An Instrument for Evaluating Media Programs"; Washington AECT Conference program; April Board of Directors meeting materials; and correspondence., 1975 (Folder 32)
  - AECT 1975 (continued): November Board of Directors meeting materials including membership report and financial statement., 1975 (Folder 33)
  - AECT Board Policy manual, constitution, and 1975 budget., 1975 (Folder 34)
  - AECT Industrial Training and Education Division: report and correspondence., 1976 (Folder 35)
  - AECT materials related to Brong's candidacy for association president., 1977-1979 (Folder 36)
  - AECT Governmental Relations Committee: correspondence; newsletters and reports; White House Conference on Library and Information Services 1979 resolutions; AECT Executive Director memorandum to Secretary of Education and testimony before Senate Labor-HEW Appropriations Subcommittee, 1980., 1979-1980 (Folder 37)
  - Certification: materials related to Washington State certification of library personnel including 1979 Certification Report to Washington State Board for Certification of Librarians by Margaret K. Goggin; materials from AECT Certification Committee., 1976-1980 (Folder 38)
  - National Commission on Libraries and Information Science (NCLIS), Washington, D.C., Mayor's Pre-White House Conference on Libraries and Information Services held 1978 September 28-30: conference materials., 1974, 1977-1978 (Folder 39)
  - NCLIS Report of Task Force on the Role of the School Library Media Program in School Networking and related correspondence., 1978 (Folder 40)
  - National Education Association, Division of Audiovisual Instruction (DAVI) Scholarship: application and correspondence., 1967-1968, 1970 (Folder 41)
  - Political advocacy: correspondence and materials related to various federal legislative efforts including: Educational Technology Act; amendments to and appropriations for provisions of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act, National Defense Education Act, Higher Education Act; appropriations for library-related issues such as cataloging, instructional technology and materials; and authorization for the White House Conference on Libraries and Information Services., 1968-1975 (Folder 42)
- Series 3: Washington State University (WSU) Committees and Projects, 1970-1979
  Series scope and content: This series gathers memoranda and materials distributed to and by WSU Library Faculty.
  - Holland (Humanities/Social Sciences) Library: information regarding planning for a Science Library separate from Humanities/Social Sciences Library, library facilities planning, reports from Faculty Senate Library Committee., 1970-1974 (Folder 43)
  - Communications to Library Faculty including salary studies, annual review process, and collective bargaining proposal., 1970-1978 (Folder 44)
  - Involvement of Instructional Media Services in proposal by Phillip H. Cheng of WSU's Communications Department for Chinese Opera filming: correspondence and proposal., 1978 (Folder 45)
  - WSU Booth at Western Washington Fair, Puyallup: correspondence, notes, exhibit list., 1979 (Folder 46)